Hello and welcome to another walkthrough for
computer architecture for everybody. We're
playing with our 6504 emulator programming and
kind of working through some increasingly complex
samples as we go. So we're going to go into
the uppercase sample. Now the previous thing
we did was a loop and this is really more of
an if test. We're not this. We're not going
to do a loop in the next thing. We're going
to have an if test um and a uh a loop. So,
we're going to we're not going to store any data
here. We're going to just it's really simple.
We're just doing an if statement. We're going
to check in this one hard-coded variables. We're
going to check to see if P is greater than or
less than A. So, we're going to load accum into A,
the P letter, the constant P. We're going to
compare the constant A with the accumulator.
And if it is, and we're doing a a convert to
uppercase here. If it's already uppercase,
we're going to skip down. And if it's not
uppercase, we're going to convert it to
uppercase. And this will only work for lowercase
A through Z, but you get the idea. Okay? And so,
uh, so let's let's take a look here. Um, convert
to uppercase. So let's go ahead and so if we look
at these things, we got a load, we got our comp,
we got our immediate, so that's the letter P,
we got our compare, and then we have our
immediate, which is the letter A. And then we
have the branch if minus down to. And the branch
of minus is really skipping this subtraction and
going all the way to eight. So the if then else
that we've kind of got here is if it's minus,
we're going to skip down two instructions
to eight. If it is not minus, we're going
to run six and then that's going to be a subtract
immediate of 0x20. Hopefully you kind of see that
that's a two and that's a zero because the 0x20.
You can see those you at some point you should
start seeing the hex. Okay, let's go ahead and
just run this at full speed and maybe I'll talk a
little bit about it afterwards. I'm just going to
turn on narration and fire. Uh oh, no. I'm going
to step. I'm going to step. So, let's do the first
one. Let's load the letter P into the accumulator.
Load accumulator.
So that's a 0x70 which is lowercase P and ASKI.
Oh, hang on. Let me bring up the ASKI chart,
right? So now we can bring up the ASKI chart.
So that's kind of fun. So I got this little
ASKI chart for you. Quick computation. So 0x70
is a hopefully a lowercase P. Look at that. So
0x70 is a lowercase P. The assembler converted
this from a quote p quote which is one of its
many load accumulator uh syntaxes and it
chened it into 011 uh 011 0 0 and which
is the letter P. Now we're going to compare
this with the letter A. So where is that?
This is the we're instruction two now and we're
going to compare it with the A. And A is just
61 hex. And there it is. 61 hex. And so
let's just compare it. Run one instruction.
basically have it set so that P which was
in the accumulator is greater than A. So
we we're not we didn't set the zero flag and we
didn't set the negative flag. Okay? And if this
character that we just compared is less than
a then we're going to skip. If it's not we're
going to subtract 20 from it. So it's not going
to be very exciting. This is going to become
0x50 because we're going to subtract 0x20. So
let's go ahead and run that step. PC4 branch.
So the branch didn't get taken. It fell right
through into position 0x06. And now we're
going to do a subtract PC. Subtract with carry
immediate 0x20. So now the next instruction is
to stop. But you'll notice that we did subtract
that 70 from the the accumulator was 70 which
is the letter where were we the letter P and we
subtracted 20 hex to it which just happens to be
uppercase P. So this was a convert to uppercase
operation and the last step is just to stop PC08.
So we didn't store anything. We just are
showing a simple if then else which turns
into a sort of compare and skip based
on flag values. Okay. So, I hope you
found this particular useful uh in the in the
walkthrough and uh cheers and see you on the